So today's דף *daf* is דף ד' *daf daled*, we pick up
with the משנה Mishna *mishna* on the bottom of ג' עמוד ב'
*gimmel amud bet*. I
actually, I think I just, whatever, slightly misread a line and just
to quickly correct it at the end of yesterday, right before it
begins, the משנה Mishna *mishna* begins, it said, you know, the issue
about the כהנים Kohanim, *Kohanim* that were claiming that they didn't have
to contribute because then it would be a קרבן Corban *korban* of
the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim*. So I just want to read this slightly,
anyway, just one line just for the sake of accuracy. It was
saying that the position of רב בן בוכרי *Rav Ben Buchri* is
הוא מוסיב לו *Hu Moshiv Lo* and he challenged the חכמים Chachamim
*Chachamim* and said זו לא lo נדבת יחיד *Zu Lo Nidvas Yachid*,
isn't it? This is like the, you know, when the כהנים Kohanim
*Kohanim* give they're actually giving private funds and doesn't that make the
קרבן Corban, *korban* a private קרבן Corban *korban*? And the response is
ואינון מוסיבין ליה *V'Inun Mosvin Leh* and they would respond to him
כיון שנמסרו לציבור כמוסו הוא נדבת ציבור *Keivan She'Nimtseru L'Tzibur K'Moshe Hu
Nidvas Tzibur*. So essentially explained it correctly, but I think what I
missed yesterday was that that was the exchange between the two sides
and their response was you cannot claim this is an individual קרבן
korban, *korban*. Once you're giving it for the communal קרבן korban, *korban*,
even if it comes from individual funds, it becomes communal funds and
therefore the כהנים *Kohanim*'s claim that they are exempt according to רבי
יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai *Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai* was
completely spurious, although they did it obviously towards their own benefit. And
now we pick up in the next משנה Mishna *mishna*, so let's
take a look. Bottom of ג' עמוד ב' *gimmel amud bet*. אף
על פי שאמרו af al pi she'amru. אין ein ממשכנין Memashkein, נשים
ועבדים וקטנים *Af al pi she'amru ein memashkinin nashim va'avadim u'ketanim*, even
though they said you do not seize the property for the debt
of women, slaves, and minors, who to pay the half-שקל Shekel *shekel*
because they aren't even obligated in the half-שקל Shekel, *shekel*, but so
you would seize property after a certain period of the for the
men but not for these, for the free men but not for
these. אבל אם שקלו מקבלין מידן *Aval im shaklu mekablin mi'yadam*, but
if they actually want to give, you certainly will accept their money
and that's not a problem. We actually learned yesterday about the קטנים
*ktanim* once they are בר מצווה bar mitzvah, *bar mitzvah*ed even if,
even though they're under twenty, twenty becoming the age patterned after the
שקל Shekel *shekel* of the תורה Torah *Torah*, one area in הלכה
halacha *halacha* where twenty matters, but by קטנים *ktanim* you actually ask
them to give once they're בר מצווה bar mitzvah. *bar mitzvah*ed and
under twenty. Here the משנה Mishnah *mishna* says that you don't ask
but you will accept donations but of course if they don't give
you will not be ממשכן *memashken*, you will not seize their property.
Since because I had meant to read yesterday because we mentioned this
idea of ממשכן *memashken* seizing property which might seem a little harsh
in the context of giving this money for קרבנות Korbanot *korbanot* and
so on, I wanted to just read you a line from the
תוספתא Tosefta *Tosefta* in שקלים Shekels, *Shekalim* about this idea of ממשכנין
*memashkenin* of seizing property. And it says like this, it says משכנו
ישראל על שקליהן
*Mashkenu Yisrael al shikleihen*, so התחילו למשכן *hitchilu l'mashken*, they would they
would begin right by the twenty-fifth of אדר *Adar* when it was
getting very close and people hadn't given, they would begin to seize
property, hold it in collateral. משכנו ישראל על שקליהן כדי שיהיו קרבנות
ציבור Korbanot Tzibur קריבין מהם Meihem *Mashkenu Yisrael al shikleihen k'dei she'yehu
korbanot tzibur kreivin mei'hem*, in order that it should be a communal
sacrifice. And then the תוספתא *Tosefta* gives a fascinating משל *mashal*. משל
לאחד שעלתה לו מכה ברגלו *Mashal l'echad she'alsa lo maka b'raglo*, somebody
had some type of an injury on his leg. והיה רופא כופתו
ומחתך בבשרו *V'haya rofe kofeto u'mechattech b'visaro* and the doctor would have
to tie him down and cut out, excise, you know, this the
infected skin.
בשביל לרפאותו *Bishvil l'rafoso*, in order to heal him. כך אמר Amar
המקום *Kach
amar ha'Makom*, so so says God, משכנו את ישראל על שקליהן *Mashkenu
et Yisrael al shikleihen*, you know, take the property in order that
they give their שקל Shekel, *shekel*. כדי שיהיו קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibur,
קריבין מהם מפני שקרבנות ציבור מרצין ומכפרין בין ישראל לאביהם שבשמים *K'dei
she'yehu korbanot tzibur kreivin mei'hem mipnei she'korbanot tzibur mirtzin u'mechapprin bein Yisrael
l'avihem she'bashamayim*. So very, that's a תוספתא פרק א' תוספתא ב' *Tosefta
Perek Aleph Tosefta Bet*. So fascinating little משל *mashal*, it recognizes the
almost the, my God, you're talking about giving to the קרבנות korbanot,
*korbanot* and all of a sudden you're talking about seizing property? He
says, yes, it's in your best interest. This way it's truly a
communal sacrifice and you have a portion. Sometimes we have to do
things against your will that we know are in your best interest.
Generally speaking, I mean, it can't be that they're seizing that much.
How much is a half-שקל Shekel. *shekel*? 25 cents? Right, it was
worth far more in ancient times.
And price of silver plummeted by about 90 percent.
Wait, how much would that be?
Okay, Michael, we are very wealthy comparatively. If you have, if all
you have to your name is a chicken, then a half-שקל Shekel,
*shekel* is a lot of money.
It's not like you're taking their
like house you know or their land.
Alright, you take like a silver
back then was probably worth what gold is today.
Okay, so let's keep on going. So that's the idea of ממשכן
*memashken*. Now it seems obvious that you'll take funds, I mean you
won't seize property, if you want to donate sure we'll take money
but not let's continue reading the משנה Mishnah, *mishna*. הנכרי והכותי ששקלו
אין מקבלין מהן *Ha'nochri v'ha'kuti she'shiklu ein mekablin mei'hen*. However if the
non-Jew or the Samaritan want to contribute their שקל Shekel *shekel* you
refuse to accept it because this is a fascinating idea but recognize
this is not necessarily money that's just going into our general operating
fund. This is money that's going into the קרבנות korbanos ציבור *korbanot
tzibur*. So the ציבור *tzibur* represents the ציבור *tzibur*. If you want
to bring your own קרבן korban, *korban* or you want to just
make a סתם Stam *stam* donation געזונטהייט *gezuntheid*, but the קרבן korban,
ציבור *korban tzibur* represents... Represents the Jewish community, and therefore this is
a place where we're going to draw the lines in terms of
who do we assume is part of the community and not part
of the community.
So okay, the אין מקבלין מידן ein mekablin miyadan, and not only
do you not accept those contributions, but you also don't accept contributions
from them of קיני זבין וקיני זבות, Kinei Zavin veKinei Zavot, birds
brought for a זב Zav and a זבה, Zava, which is interesting,
it doesn't even apply to non-Jews. וקיני יולדת veKinei Yoledet or birds
brought for a יולדת Yoledet sacrifice, וחטאות ואשמות veChatot veAshamot and sin
offerings. Meaning that they can give free will offerings. You want to
make סתם Stam a contribution of funds, you want to bring a
קרבן korban. that's an עולה Olah free will קרבן, korban but a
קרבן korban. that is an obligation, that's part of your Jewish identity,
being part of the Jewish community, this sense of obligatory קרבנות korbanos.
is part of a Jewish obligation. That is something that we will
refuse to accept from somebody that is not part of the community.
זה הכלל, Ze HaKlal, this is the rule. כל שנידר ונידב מקבלין
מידן. Kol sheNiddar veNidav mekablin miyadan. Anything that is, you know, free
will contribution, we will accept from them. כל שאינו נידר ונידב Kol
sheEino Niddar veNidav or לא נידר ולא נידב, lo Niddar veLo Nidav,
anything that is not free will, that is some sense of obligation,
and שקל Shekel also is obligatory,
אין מקבלין מידן, you do not accept it from their hands. וכן
מפורש על ידי עזרא, veChen Meforash al yedei Ezra, and this is
actually clear in the פסוקים Psukim in Ezra, שנאמר: sheNe'emar: לא לכם
ולנו לבנות בית לאלהינו. Lo lachem velanu livnot bayit l'Eloheinu. This is
when actually the Samaritans when they came back to the land in
the בית שני Bayit Sheni and the Samaritans first were very opposed
and giving them a lot of צרות Tzaros and a certain stage
they said hey, participate with you? And the response was, "No, this
is the house of our God, this is not your temple, it's
our temple." And they wanted to actually draw those lines and say
that, you know, that on the one hand, you know, we'll accept
contributions, but on the other hand, you know, in certain areas, but
on the other hand, not in a way that is going to
blur the sense of what is the boundaries of our community and
whose temple is this? Because obviously if they're, you know,
particularly in those times, you could have also imagined that if they
would have accepted the money, then the claim would have been that
it's not just a Jewish temple, it's a Samaritan temple as well
and so on. Yes.
So there are תנאי Tannaic opinions that the Samaritans actually do count.
So the גמרא Gemara
will discuss that.
So the גמרא Gemara will discuss that. It's clear from the פסוקים
Psukim that whether technically they counted let's say at an individual level
as a Jew, you know, you presented yourself and you wanted to,
you know, as a Samaritan, and I don't know, you wanted to
whatever, do something as an individual, but clearly they existed as a
distinct community and a distinct and almost, you know,
antagonistic community at least in the early temple times. So the idea
that as a, you know, you want to draw those communal boundaries
even if like technically the person might be Jewish, it raises those
interesting questions, right? Because the question were Samaritans Jewish or not is
an abstract הלכתי Halachic issue, but there's also facts on the ground
about how they organized themselves as a distinct community, and that was
at both sides of the equation, right? So but we will discuss
that when we get to the גמרא. Gemara. ואלו שחייבין בקלבון. veEilu
sheChayavin beKalbon.
Now the משנה Mishnah, turns into a definition—these are a couple of
משניות Mishnayot I should say strung together. This is a totally different
point, which is a קלבון Kalbon is basically a small amount,
a whatever we'll find out what exactly it is, like a four
percent or something or
of a fee that was given to the money changer. And presumably
what this was about was if you bring not an exact half
שקל, Shekel, you bring a שקל Shekel and you expect change, so
they take a little bit of a commission. Okay, so this was
the money changer's commission. Okay, so the following people are obligated to
pay this money changer's commission: לויים וישראלים וגרים ועבדים משוחררים. Leviyim veYisraeliyim
veGeirim vaAvadim Meshuchrarim. Okay, so all the people that are obligated in
the in the שקל, Shekel אבל לא Aval Lo but not, כהנים
ונשים ועבדים וקטנים. Kohanim veNashim vaAvadim uKetanim. Now, not כהנים, women, slaves,
and minors. So women, slaves, and minors we understand, they were exempt,
and therefore if you want to contribute, you know, we're not going
to also charge you a commission if you're just being nice and
giving a free contribution to the half שקל. Shekel, But כהנים presumably,
we're going to like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan בן זכאי are obligated,
but nevertheless remember even if כהנים are obligated, we don't, we're not
ממשכנין, we don't seize the property out of כבוד. Kavod. We don't
want to sort of, you know, so therefore presumably in a similar
vein, we would say even though you're obligated, we'll sort of go
easy—professional courtesy, exactly. And we're going to waive the small little money
changer's fee. Okay, you know, anyway, you had to make them feel
important because they were obviously resisting giving in the first place.
But these were employees of the temple essentially?
What? These money changers? Yeah, employees of the temple. Okay, I mean
there's a question whether they sort of—whether they—what do you call it?
Had some of the no not yeah, but I was actually saying
like you know, contracted it out, whether they subcontracted the actual process.
Because if they're independent operators then why can't they charge their commission?
Right, so we're going to see that this was not the choice,
exactly. It was not the choice of the individual money changer. These
are people like it says, they set up their tables in the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. These were people that were employees of the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Right. השוקל על ידי כהן על ידי אשה.
haShokel al yedei Kohen al yedei Isha. Right. השוקל על ידי כהן
על ידי אשה על ידי עבד על ידי קטן פטור. HaShokel Al
Yedei Kohen Al Yedei Isha Al Yedei Eved Al Yedei Katan Patur.
Let's say you go ahead and you say, I'm going to give
a whole שקל, Shekel two half, which is two half שקלים, Shekels.
right? So you don't have to break it into, you only have
to break it into if you're going to give me change. But
I'm going to make it easy on you. You don't have to
give me change. I'm giving this whole שקל Shekel for me and
my friend the כהן, Kohen, or for me and for my wife,
or for me and for my child. So somebody that normally if
they were giving themselves wouldn't pay anyway a money changer fee. So
in that type of a case even though you're paying, but you're
doing it for you and for somebody who would be exempt, you're
exempt. Of course the other point being you're giving a whole שקל
Shekel they don't even have to make change. Okay, so I understand,
but interestingly we're going to see it does make a difference. Okay?
But if one of the people you're giving for is exempt and
you're giving a whole שקל, Shekel then you don't pay this fee.
ואם שקל על ידו ועל ידי חברו חייב בקולבון אחד. Veim Shakal
Al Yado Ve'al Yedei Havero Hayav Bekolbon Echad. Now that's a very
strange idea. I'm giving a שקל Shekel this is for me and
Michael, then I actually have to pay the fee. Even though if
I was giving, even though nobody has to make change for me.
So this becomes, I really can't explain it. This somehow just becomes
a standard fee that is charged. And somehow we say, since if
each of you were giving individually you would each give a fee,
even though now you're joining together and we don't even have to
break up the money. You know it's sort of like, you know
what that thing from the, a line in the fiddler or the
fiddle or whatever because you had a bad day, why should I
suffer? You know just because, just because you're giving together why should
we not get our money changes fee. Of course there's an obvious
reason, you're not making change, but okay. And so you'll pay one
fee, you won't pay two fees, but you still have to pay
one. I really can't explain it, okay.
I would say like that's the case anyway because if you're talking
about שקל Shekel. and half שקל, Shekel what do you need the
money changers for? Presumably the treasury has an oversupply of
half שקלים.
Making change not a big deal.
Right, that's a good point. So maybe you're meaning, so what you're
saying is really it's not so much for the cost of, it's
really just like a fee for the service of being there. That's
a good way of thinking about it.
Or you just had to hire people, you had to hire people
to sit there and collect the money. So that's a good way
of thinking about it. You know that's a good way of thinking
about it that it's not actually for the cost of making the
change, it's for the cost of doing the whole of
running the whole business.
Like when you give money to the שול Shul online you have
a choice to...
Right right, like a transaction, that's a good example, like an online
transaction fee or something like that.
I'm not going to argue against the analogy that is like the
whole thing.
Okay, no but it's a very good point. I'm always thinking about
it as a fee for making change but you're right it's really
a fee for the whole transaction. That's a much better way of
thinking about it. Okay so even though you've bundled it up in
one transaction you still have to pay at least one fee not
two fees. That's better, think of it like as a transaction fee.
So interestingly though when you bundled it up with somebody that's exempt
you get exempt as well. You piggyback on their exemption. Okay. רבי
מאיר אומר ב' קולבונות. Rabbi Meir Omer Beis Kolbonot. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says no, even in that case you pay two fees, even
though it was one transaction. And we'll see in the גמרא Gemara
why this is, basically I'll just tell you that רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir feels that no שקל Shekel will
ever be completely pure, will always have some impurities. So like as
a little bit of a margin of error, you know a little
bit of making sure you have the full amount you add a
little bit extra.
Even for half שקל Shekel then?
It is. He says even if you give a straight half שקל
Shekel, you always have to pay this fee. So every half שקל
Shekel requires a little margin of error, a little extra bit, according
to רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. Does that assume that that little commission goes to the
מקדש? Mikdash?
Yes,
so then there's going to be a discussion where does the money
go to. And according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir it goes to
the same fund and that's an excellent point. How we think about
the purpose of this fee, it's debated in the תוספתא what this
is done with this money. And not surprisingly רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says this money goes to the קרבנות korbanos, ציבור goes the exact
same place the שקל Shekel. goes. Whereas others say no, it goes
to the שולחני Shulchani and it goes to other types of sort
of temple funds. So that's an excellent point. So according to the
חכמים Chachamim I think it's been very well sort of said it's
not really the fee for making change, it's a transaction fee. If
you do one transaction even though it's two you only pay one.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no, it's an extra amount you add
to every half שקל. shekel הנותן סלע ונוטל שקל. HaNoten Sela VeNotel
Shekel. Now it's a little confusing here because סלע Sela in the
משנה Mishnah was actually the שקל shekel, of the תורה Torah, and
שקל shekel. of the משנה Mishnah was actually the half שקל shekel.
of the תורה, Torah, just to confuse you. So you give a
סלע Sela and you get back a שקל, shekel. which basically means
you gave a שקל shekel and you got back your half שקל.
shekel, Okay, so you actually made change here. In this case חייב
שני קולבונות. Hayav Shenei Kolbonot. You pay two of these fees. So
again, I didn't understand it but I think that what you said
is very helpful. In this case you pay two, one is the
transaction fee and one is the change fee. So actually in this
case, right, any transaction you pay this fee for cost and in
this case you're also making change, so you actually pay. another.
Right, so let's see as the משנה Mishnah continues. השוקל על ידי
עני ועל ידי שכנו ועל ידי בן עירו. HaShokel al yedei ani
v'al yedei shecheino v'al yedei ben iro. Let's say you are, now
this the way this is assumed to be different than the case
before when you're giving for yourself and your friend is there you
were lending your friend the money. Here you actually are being a
צדיק tzaddik and you're paying for another person. You're not lending them
the money. I'm giving a שקל shekel for me and for that
poor person near my house, I'm just going to give it to
him so he doesn't have to take it out of his own
pocket. In that case you're being such a צדיק, tzaddik, that's sort
of clear from the עני, ani, not so clear from שכינו shecheino
and בן עירו, ben iro, but in that case פטור patur we'll
waive the transaction fee. Okay, so if you're giving for two people
but both of you are really giving, we'll charge the fee, but
if you're basically being nice to somebody and paying for them, you
get a waiver of the fee. ואם הלוון, V'im hilvan, but if
you're only lending them the money, so that turns up to the
earlier case, then חייב chayav you still have to pay that transaction
fee. We're not worrying about רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir right now. האחים
השותפין שחייבים בקולבון פטורים ממעשר בהמה. Ha'achim hashutafin shechayavim bakolbon paturim mima'aser
behema. So brothers who are, somehow this has two cases, we'll read
it for simplicity as one. Brothers who are partners who are obligated
in the קולבון kolbon are exempt from מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behema. What
does this mean? It means that one of the few places in
הלכה halacha that you find the idea of a corporate entity is
in the idea of an estate that has not yet been divided.
And an estate that has not yet been divided that was inherited
by you know brothers, by children, in that case it's owned multiple
people own it, but it's not a partnership. It's not like multiple
separate owners each one as an individual you know sort of partner.
It's the corporate entity of the estate. And as that, as that,
it's conceptually like one person, right? Is a corporation a person, right?
Was a whole recent Supreme Court thing. So that's one person. So
if that estate owns animals, the הלכה is שותף, shuttaf, if you're
a שותף shuttaf in an animal, it's exempt from מעשר בהמה. ma'aser
behema. So if that estate owns animals, they're חייב chayav in מעשר
בהמה ma'aser behema if it exists as an estate as a single
entity. And similarly, if you're one entity, you are exempt in multiple
קולבונות kolbonot because you're only one. Now even if that entity has
to give for all of the brothers, so that's sort of by
some מפרשים meforshim that's compared to the idea of like the father
who gives for his children and therefore right when you give for
your children you don't pay the קולבון. kolbon. So even though it
might have to give multiple חצי שקלים, chatzi shekalim,
fundamentally it's one entity and therefore it does not pay multiple קולבונות
kolbonot and it's פטור patur from the קולבון. kolbon. If however they
divided the estate and then they
regrouped as some type of a partnership, then as a partnership it's
not a corporation and as a partnership they would be פטור patur
from מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behema. Partnership is פטור patur from מעשר בהמה
ma'aser behema and they'd be חייב chayav in קולבון kolbon because they
are multiple individuals joined together as opposed to one corporate entity. Interesting
to note that although many מפרשים meforshim read this as one case,
אחים השותפין, achim hashutafin, brothers who are partners, רמב"ם Rambam actually reads
it as two. And רמב"ם Rambam actually allows for an idea of
a normal partnership becoming somewhat like a corporate entity, which is for
us obvious but actually is very hard to find in the הלכתי
halachic literature the concept of a corporation. רמב"ם Rambam actually thinks that
something like that can exist and sees that you can even have
a partnership that works like this estate and like a corporation. So
let's read that again.
האחים השותפין שחייבים בקולבון, Ha'achim hashutafin shechayavim bakolbon, when this type of
partnership estate is obligated in the קולבון, kolbon, meaning that it's a
partnership, פטורים ממעשר בהמה. paturim mima'aser behema. They're exempt from מעשר בהמה.
ma'aser behema. כשחייבים במעשר בהמה, K'shechayavim b'ma'aser behema, when they're obligated in
מעשר בהמה, ma'aser behema, פטורים מן הקולבון, paturim min hakolbon, then they
are one estate and then they're exempt from the קולבון kolbon because
it's like one entity. וכמה הוא הקולבון, V'kamah hu hakolbon, how much
is the קולבון? kolbon? מעה כסף, Ma'ah kesef, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei
Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says a מעה ma'ah which is
a twenty-fourth of a סלע, sela, which as a סלע sela is
a full שקל, shekel, not a half שקל. shekel So that would
be a twelfth of the half שקל. shekel וחכמים אומרים חצי מעה,
Vachachamim omrim chatzi ma'ah, the חכמים Chachamim say a twenty-fourth. So according
to the חכמים it's about four percent added to your half שקל.
shekel, I don't know what normal commission fee is, it's probably less
than four percent. Okay, yes, Mike, what's your question?
I want to understand what's the difference between let's say you're paying
for me, you know, when or loaning me, then you're חייב chayav
in this thing and you say oh no no we're partners.
I mean how can you, because if you're partners every individual
is obligated and then it's a case of like
at most you would have a case of הלווהו, hilvahu, right, if
one person is giving, but then it's חייב chayav for you know
for one קולבון kolbon whereas if you're giving for somebody else, I'm
saying like how can they prove it, you know let's hold off
on it okay? I want to get a little bit further in
the גמרא. Gemara. We'll worry about the אחים השותפין achim hashutafin in
a minute. Yes.
Can I ask you a question? על יד al yad or על
ידי al yedei usually means through the agency of. Right. So this
is an idiomatic...
yeah it's true. You could say it means the עבד eved is
the one paying, but no, it's clear here it means... for the
sake of. Right. That's correct.
Even though here it's different.
Right. You would have thought the roles are reversed. That's correct. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אף על פי שאמרו. So
the גמרא Gemara says, even though we said, you know, you don't
seize the property of a קטן, katan, but you'll accept gifts. So
the גמרא Gemara says הליטבועה אין תובעין. halitvoha ein tovin. It sounds
like though you won't make any demands. הכא את אמר תובעין והכא
את אמר אין תובעין. hacha at amar tovin vehacha at amar ein
tovin. Here, meaning based on the earlier משנה, Mishnah remember yesterday we
said we actually ask minors to give, and here you're saying we
don't ask, we'll only accept if they give? כאן שהביא בשערו וכאן
שלא הביא בשערו. kan shehevi besaro vekan shelo hevi besaro. No, the
resolution is, when they have two hair, pubic hairs, they're בר מצווה,
then we'll make demands, but we won't actually
obligate it, we'll ask, we won't obligate it until they're twenty years
old. When our משנה, Mishnah, what it sounds like you don't even
ask for it, that is when they are under בר מצווה. Okay,
now we get to the new point, which is not accepting it
from non-Jews and Samaritans. הנוכרי והכותי. hanochri vehakuti.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי בא, amar Rabbi Ba, so
says רבי בא, Rabbi Ba, or רבי אבא Rabbi Abba probably is,
תיפתר, tipater, you should explain it כמאן דאמר כותי כנוכרי. keman de'amar
kuti kanochri. This is going according to the opinion that says, like
as Charlie pointed out, a כותי kuti is like a non-Jew. תיפלוג,
tiplog, because this is a debate. כותי כנוכרי דברי רבי, kuti kanochri
divrei rebbi, רבי Rebbi says a Samaritan has the status of a
non-Jew, they did not really convert.
רבן גמליאל אמר כותי כישראל לכל דבר, Rabban Gamliel omer kuti kiyisrael
lechol davar, no, they're actually Jews, they actually did convert. So אמר
רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, so it sounds like they're non-Jews? So
אמר רבי אלעזר מתניתין בנוכרי, amar Rabbi Elazar matnitin banochri,
our משנה Mishnah is talking about non-Jews. הבכותים לא, habakutim lo, but
not by Samaritans. Now, what does that mean? The משנה Mishnah explicitly
says הנוכרי והכותי ששקלו אין מקבלין מידיהן. hanochri vehakuti sheshaklu ein mekabelin
miyadeihan. So what he is saying, the way the מפרשים mefarshim try
to explain what he is saying is, it's going on the second
part of it, when it says when they bring different קרבנות, korbanos.
זבים, zavim, זבות, zavot, יולדת, yoledet, חטאת ואשמות, chatat veashamot, etc., there
it's not so clear anymore exactly who we're talking about, and he
says that's only about non-Jews. Samaritans you would accept their קרבן, korban.
and the logic here is exactly I think what I said before
when I responded to Charlie, which is technically they could be, he's
saying, you say our משנה Mishnah is only assuming Samaritans are non-Jews?
Not necessarily. Samaritans might be Jews, but in the context of the
קרבנות korbanos, ציבור, you know, and if you look at the פסוק
pasuk in עזרא, Ezra, building the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, where there
they had a whole different temple and they clearly were distinct community
and so on, it was very important at that stage to draw
communal lines even if technically speaking they were Jews. On the other
hand, when it comes to as an individual they want to bring
a קרבן, korban they want to make a donation, so then you
could accept it from them. So the second part of our משנה
Mishnah actually is only by non-Jews, Samaritans would be different, Samaritans technically
are Jews. There's still places that we will draw the line. By
the way, רמב"ם Rambam rules this way. רמב"ם Rambam rules that, you
know, you don't accept their, you know, you don't take their שקל
shekel and so on, he says but if a Samaritan brings a
קרבן חטאת, korban chatat, even an obligatory קרבן, you would accept it
from them. You give them an opportunity, maybe they'll want to do
תשובה, teshuva, maybe they'll want to eventually, you know, become like a
rabbinic Jew and not a Samaritan Jew. So it's interesting thinking about
the question of personal status as opposed to also communal boundaries and
lines. By the way, if this גמרא Gemara is disturbing people, which
it might be, about insisting on these lines, I just want to
point out, I don't know if this makes things better or worse,
but there's actually a very sad chapter in the history in terms
of Samaritan-Jewish relations. You know,
the Samaritans continued through the, well actually, actually this isn't fair, this
isn't Samaritans, this is Karaites. Okay, but it's an interesting parallel. The
Karaites, Karaite community as people know, there's like a small Karaite community
in Israel, whatever, there were Karaites in Eastern Europe up to the
time or through the time, thousands, a big Karaite community in the
time in Poland at the time of the Holocaust. The Karaites convinced
the Nazis that they weren't Jews, and the Karaites actually were not,
you know, were not persecuted and were not exterminated during the Holocaust,
and the Jewish community tried to get some names of some people
on the list in the Karaite communities of who was a Karaite
so that they would be spared and the Karaites refused to put
any non-Karaite on the list. So just to, you know, point out
about sometimes this issue about boundaries obviously has very tragic, tragic consequences,
but you know, anyway, so and also they were persecuted by rabbinic
Jews. Well, that's
also, so obviously, right, so it's not like it came out of
nowhere, that's true. But you know, sometimes it worked in the reverse,
the Karaites were when they were stronger were very, you know, were
very aggressive against rabbinic Jews as well, so anyway, alright, back, so
let's take a look. So anyway, so, so
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar has a fascinating position where he says that
actually the Samaritans could be Jews, excluded from part of the משנה,
Mishnah but not from the other part. of the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*.
אבל בנכרי *Aval benochri* so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this:
מתניתין בנכרי, אבל כותים Kutim, לא *Mattinitin benochri, aval Kutim lo*. ותני
כן *Vetani ken* we taught similarly, אדם adam *Adam* the פסוק pasuk
*Pasuk* is in the beginning of ויקרא *Vayikra* אדם כי יקריב מכם
קרבן לה' *Adam ki yakriv mikem korban la-Hashem*. אדם לרבות את הגרים
*Adam lerabbos es hagerim* includes גרים *gerim*. Now that's interesting. Why does
גרים *gerim* even have to be included? So it's interesting, some מדרשי
הלכה *Midreshei Halacha* feel the need to say that it includes גרים
*gerim* even though you know the פסוק posuk *Pasuk* says כגר כאזרח
יהיה *kager ka'ezrach yihiyeh* and equates a גר *ger* for all הלכות
*halachos*. Other versions of this דרשה *drasha* have אדם אפילו נכרים *Adam
afilu nochrim* that even a non-Jew can bring a קרבן *korban*, right?
Because as our משנה mishna *Mishnah* indicated, a non-Jew can bring an
עולה olah. *olah*, just can't bring an obligatory sacrifice. Okay, so on
the one hand we're including... starts with an עולה olah? *olah* anyway.
Right, well that's my point. מכם *Mikem*, from among you, להוציא את
המומרים *lehotzi es hamumrim*, but an apostate, a... that person cannot bring
a קרבן *korban*. Okay, so now what does that prove? So it
doesn't really prove much but in terms of that... hold on let
me just see how the קרבן העדה *Korban HaEdah* explains why... what
proof that... what the proof there is...
one minute...
yeah I'm not exactly sure what that's supposed to prove.
One minute let me just...
yeah, so what one of the מפרשים mefarshim *Meforshim* just says is
go גרים *gerim* obviously includes כותים Kutim? *Kutim*. So I mean that
which is really begging the question right whether Samaritans were גרים *gerim*
or not. So it's a little bit unclear what that is supposed
to prove. So then let's see as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
מתניתין פליג על רבי אליעזר *Masnisin palig al Rabbi Eliezer*. Our משנה
mishna *Mishnah* seems to contradict Rabbi Eliezer's claim. Rabbi Eliezer says the
end of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* is only talking about non-Jews. Let's
look at the end of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. וכי יש yesh
קיני זבים וזבות בנכרים *Vechi yesh kinei zavim vezavos banochrim*? The end
of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* says... I'm sorry I skipped a line.
אין מקבלים מידם קיני זבים וזבות וקיני יולדות *Ein mekabelim miyadam kinei
zavim vezavos vekinei yoldos*. What does it say you don't accept? Which
this second part of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*, which Rabbi Eliezer says
is talking only about non-Jews. It says obligatory sacrifices like the birds
that are brought for זב *zav* and a זבה *zavah* and a
woman who gave... who gave birth. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
you don't have to tell me you don't accept that from a
non-Jew. וכי יש קיני זבים וזבות בנכרים *Vechi yesh kinei zavim vezavos
banochrim*? Non-Jews don't even have that whole category. So obviously you don't
accept it from a non-Jew. So clearly if it says you don't
accept it, it must be talking about somebody you might have thought
you would accept it from. It must be talking about a Samaritan.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so it seems pretty clear that
the end of the משנה *Mishnah* of not accepting those קרבנות *korbanos*
are talking about Samaritans where you might have thought you accept it.
אלא רישא בנכרים וסיפא בכותים *Ella reisha banochrim vesifa beKutim*. The beginning
part of the משנה *Mishnah* is by non-Jews, the end about not
accepting from the... these קרבנות *korbanos* of the... like of the woman
who gave birth, that's about Samaritans. כן הוא *Kein hu*? Or maybe
it was a question, is it true? Can we say the beginning
is by נכרים *nochrim* and the end is by כותים Kutim *Kutim*?
כן הוא *Kein hu*! Yes, רישא בנכרים וסיפא בכותים *reisha banochrim vesifa
beKutim*. The end is about non-Jews... the beginning is about non-Jews, the
end is about Samaritans. Now, that does not make sense what this
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is talking about. Look, this is, you know, I
spent a lot of time on this... after a certain point I
realized I am not going to be able to fix intrinsic problems
in this text. The text is very challenging. Look, the משנה *Mishnah*
says two things. It says you do not accept a שקל shekel
*shekel* from non-Jews and Samaritans. And then it says you don't accept
from them, which is an ambiguous phrase, these types of obligatory sacrifices
and so on. So Rabbi Eliezer says our משנה *Mishnah* is only
talking about non-Jews. Now the only part that's ambiguous is the second
part. You don't accept from them these bird sacrifices. So the גמרא
gemara *Gemara* proves that that has to be talking about Samaritans because
it was... would have been a non-starter by non-Jews, it's only a
possible discussion by Samaritans. So fine, that part is about Samaritans. So
what do you mean the beginning is about non-Jews? The beginning's explicit.
The beginning says you don't accept from non-Jews and Samaritans the half
שקל shekel *shekel*. So the best of מפרשים mefarshim, *Meforshim* say is
it means the... the beginning is talking about also non-Jews. You don't
accept from non-Jews and Samaritans the half שקל shekel *shekel*, and you
don't accept from Samaritans it goes without saying non-Jews but you don't
accept from Samaritans these types of bird sacrifices. At the end of
the day, it means you don't accept from non-Jews and Samaritans anything.
So how to say that Rabbi Eliezer still fits in the משנה
*Mishnah* is a real challenge. Okay? It seems very clear the beginning
of the משנה *Mishnah* is explicit in the text that you don't
accept the half שקל shekel, *shekel* from Samaritans and non-Jews and the
end by the case of talking about these obligatory bird sacrifices it
has to be addressing Samaritans as well. So although Rabbi Eliezer had
a fascinating position, which is Samaritans technically could be Jewish but we're
still going to choose to exclude them from some things and not
others, that seems to be rejected by the משנה *Mishnah*. That being
said, the רמב"ם *Rambam* actually says that if a Samaritan brings a
קרבן *korban* you bring... you accept it from him. א קרבן חטאת
*A korban chatas*, not only an עולה olah. *olah*. עולה olah? *Olah*
you'd accept from non-Jews. So the רמב"ם *Rambam* seems somehow, I don't
know how he reads our גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, to rule like Rabbi
Eliezer and say they might be excluded from some communal things but
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Now the גמרא Gemara shifts
to slightly easier territory.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says אמר רבי
יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan says רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. בתחילה אין מקבלים
מהם לא דבר מסוים ולא דבר שאינו מסוים. Batchila Ein Mekablim Meihem
Lo Davar Mesuyam Velo Davar She-eino Mesuyam. At the outset, meaning like
the case in עזרא Ezra where you're beginning to build the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So at the outset, you know, where people really
it's dangerous to accept certain contributions at the outset then people claim
that they have a stake and that they're partners and so on.
So at the outset you don't accept from them, presumably now we're
dealing with non-Jews or who knows, non-Jews, כותים, anyone. You don't accept
from them neither a designate, a specific thing, or a non-specific thing.
Non-specific thing, think about the way we say money is fungible, right?
דבר מסוים Davar Mesuyam is I want to donate a מנורה Menorah
that's going to sit right at the front of your front yard,
it's going to have my name on it. Okay, so that's a
little bit more questionable. Do you want to associate that with particular
groups of people? You know, if you want your identity of your
place to be a very particular, you know, identity. So he says
דבר מסוים Davar Mesuyam is more dangerous. אינו מסוים Eino Mesuyam is
just funds. Okay, so he says at the beginning we don't accept
funds even even unspecified funds from anyone. Okay, from from non-Jews. Okay
לא דבר מסוים ולא דבר שאינו מסוים. Lo Davar Mesuyam Velo Davar
She-eino Mesuyam. ובסוף, Uvesof, once we're underway or once the place is
built and maybe we want to make some repairs or various types
of things, it's very clear what the identity of the place is.
In that case מקבלים מהם דבר שאינו מסוים Mekablim Meihem Davar She-eino
Mesuyam we can take, you know, sort of non-you know, general funds.
Okay, ואין מקבלים מהם דבר מסוים Ve-ein Mekablim Meihem Davar Mesuyam you
cannot accept from them something specific. You can't accept from them like,
you know, here's this מנורה Menorah that I'm giving and I want
it erected and I want a plaque on it with my name.
So that you don't do. But general funds you can accept.
So they still can't let's say they said I want you to
take this money and
so we'll talk about that. Let's say they give you funds and
they say what you and they want to designate what you want
to do with it. So we'll see if a something like that
in a little bit. ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, רבי שמעון בן לקיש
Rabbi Shimon Ben Lakish אמר בין בתחילה בין בסוף Bein Batchila Bein
Besof I don't care beginning or end אין מקבלים מהם לא דבר
מסוים ולא דבר שאינו מסוים. Ein Mekablim Meihem Lo Davar Mesuyam Velo
Davar She-eino Mesuyam. You don't take from them neither specific objects or
even just general funds. So I assume ריש לקיש Reish Lakish never
had to actually raise money for any of these causes. But basically
what this shows is that there
was a tremendous amount of
interactivity on a communal level.
Yeah, I mean, look, when you when they've dug up these synagogues
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you see inscriptions about, you know, and
who they receive funds from and I think sometimes it's a clear
that they receive funds from non-Jews and there are actually inscriptions about
that if I if memory serves correctly.
And this is in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Right, and this is מהם as well as
them, presumably non-Jews.
Yeah, also כותים? I don't know. Okay, let's take a look. מתניתין
פליגא אדרבי יוחנן, Masnisin Peliga Ada-Rabbi Yochanan, the ברייתא Braisa מתניסא Masnisa
probably פליגא אדרבי יוחנן Peliga Ada-Rabbi Yochanan argues on רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan What does the ברייתא Braisa say? אין מקבלים מהם הקדש ונדבה
לבדק הבית. Ein Mekablim Meihem Hekdesh Unedava Levedek Habayis.
It says you don't accept from them, again, them generic, non-Jews and
כותים presumably, sanctified objects and donations for בדק הבית. Bedek Habayis. Now
בדק הבית Bedek Habayis is like general operating funds but also more
specifically means like a, you know, funds for repairs. So presumably it's
talking about even at the end of the once the place is
built, בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is built. Also there's an interesting question,
are they talking about just the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Are they
talking about even local synagogues? How, you know, how globally did they
mean to apply this? Okay, but anyway it says you don't accept
from them these funds for בדק הבית, Bedek Habayis, is that me?
For, sorry, for בדק הבית Bedek Habayis and it does not distinguish
between, you know, whether again, whether it is specified or non-specified. That's
even non-specified. That's even at the end of the process. פתר לה
Patar La so here's you can explain it בין בתחילה בין בסוף
Bein Batchila Bein Besof yes, we are talking about whether at the
outset or at the end of the
process. Okay, ובוודאי דבר מסוים Uvevaday Davar Mesuyam when it says you
don't accept from them, it doesn't just mean funds, it means you
don't accept from them specific objects to be used. Okay, so that's
what you don't accept. So you're right, it sounds like like ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish that you never accept anything from them, but we'll
say it's talking about when it's speaking about very concrete specific types
of objects. Wait one minute. ריש לקיש אמר בין בתחילה בין בסוף
אין מקבלים מהם לא דבר מסוים. Reish Lakish Amar Bein Batchila Bein
Besof Ein Mekablim Meihem Lo Davar Mesuyam. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says
you never accept from them anything beginning or end whether specific or
non-specific. מתניתין פליגא אריש לקיש Masnisin Peliga A-Reish Lakish the following משנה
argues on ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. It's a משנה in ערכין Arachin
דתני Detani we taught הכל שווין. Hakol Shavin. It talked about non-Jews
making an ערך, Erech, right? If you say the value of this
person is on me, so that's called מעריך Ma-arich and if you're
נערך Ne-erach you're the person who's being he's being valued. So it
says and there was an issue about non-Jews being part of the
ערך Erech process. So the משנה continues and says הכל שווין Hakol
Shavin and everybody agrees שנודרין ונידרין She-nodrin Venidrin that even though they
might not be in the category of ערך, Erech, which is a
very specific type of a donation in the תורה, Torah, of a
they all agree that non-Jews can make a נדר Neder can make
a contribution and נידרין Nidrin can be made an object of a
נדר. Neder. Now what that means an object of a נדר Neder
is not. exactly clear. We'll talk about that in a minute. But
for us the important thing is this, it says non-Jews can make
a, can be נודר, noder, can make a contribution. So presumably that's
not just talking about so so how do you explain that? רייש
לקיש Reish Lakish says you never accept any funds from them. So
the גמרא says פטר לה עולה. patar lah olah. So you can
explain no, we don't mean the נדר neder of funds to be
contributed. We mean that they can bring a קרבן, right? Our משנה
said, what did our משנה said? כל דבר זה כלל כל שנדר
ונידב מקבלין מהן. kol davar zeh klal kol she-nidar v'nidav mekablin mei-hen.
So a נדר neder and a נדבה nedavah can mean two things,
it can mean money and it can mean a נדבה nedavah a
נדר neder of a קרבן. And apparently this is the difference. If
my place is up and running and the entire place was built
with Jewish funds and you want to come into a Jewish temple
and actually you know bring a קרבן which essentially is anyway giving
acknowledgement to the Jewish God and you're a non-Jew גזונטהייט gezuntheit you
want to bring a קרבן. But the but the temple is a
Jewish temple. So there's so we'll accept your קרבנות which is you
know participating in the in the offerings of the temple we will
not accept your funds. That's what רייש לקיש Reish Lakish says. So
when the משנה says that everybody agrees non-Jews can make a נדר,
neder, it doesn't mean funds, it means bring a קרבן. פטר לה
עולה patar lah olah and that was the פסוק posuk before אדם
כי יקריב מכם עולה adam ki yakriv mikem olah that אדם even
includes a non-Jew. So the גמרא says ניחא נודרין niha nodrin fine
that's good the case of they actually make the vow themselves to
bring an עולה. olah נודרים עולה. nodrin olah. נידרים עולה nidrin olah
how do you have it? לא or again the text is obviously
is obviously a bit in question, but how do you have a
case of being vowed for an עולה? olah. I can't make a
vow on you that you have to bring an עולה. olah What
does that mean to be the object of a vow for an
עולה? olah Not to make the עולה olah vow, נידרין. nidrin. אלא
כשאמר ella keshe-amar here's the case. ישראל הרי עלי עולה Yisrael harei
alai olah you hear a Jew saying I'm going to bring an
עולה. ושמע נכרי v'shama nochri and the non-Jew hears ואמר מה שאמר
זה עלי. v'amar mah she-amar zeh alai. Yeah, what that guy said,
same for me. So that's נידרין nidrin not in the sense that
I impose the vow on you, but you're not the initiator of
the vow. I initiated the vow and the non-Jew said me too,
so he somewhat extended the vow onto himself. Okay but anyway the
end of the line is that it says non-Jews can make vows,
but we say what it means is they can bring קרבנות. According
to רייש לקיש, Reish Lakish, we never actually allow them to give
funds. Okay we're going to let's finish this we're not done with
this debate.
So the גמרא and this gets to the question about what if
you give funds that are then used to buy something specific. So
the גמרא says
ואינו מביא עמו נסכים? v'eino meivi imo nesachim? One minute, if a
non-Jew is going to bring an עולה with an עולה comes נסכים,
nesachim, wine and flour. Big deal. ומותר נסכים לא לכלי שרת אינון?
u-motar nesachim lo li-chlei shareit inun? We have a principle that any
funds that are designated for נסכים nesachim that are left over that
goes towards buying כלי שרת, klei shareit, buying vessels in the temple.
So if you accept עולות olos from a נכרי, nochri, they're going
to designate the money, there's going to be leftover money, you're going
to wind up using that for a כלי שרת. klei shareit. That's
going to turn into a דבר מסויים. davar mesuyam. How are we
going to allow that to happen? Even according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan how are we going to allow that to happen? נמצא מביא
דבר מסויים nimtza meivi davar mesuyam you wind up bringing a specific
thing. התיב רבי יוסי בר רבי בון heitiv Rabbi Yosi bar Rabbi
Bun והתנינן v'ha-teninan על נערכין ונערכין. al ne'erachin v'ne'erachin. So we
there's an opinion that says that non-Jews can be make an ערך,
erech, okay, can say ערך פלוני עלי erech ploni alai the value
of this person or they can be the object of an ערך.
erech. Now what happens what is the money when you use the
term ערך erech and you give that money? Where does that money
go? לא לבדק הבית אינון? lo l'vedek ha-bayit inun? Doesn't that money
go to the בדק הבית? bedek ha-bayit? And that should at least
be a question according to רייש לקיש. Reish Lakish. According to how
do you explain the opinion that a non-Jew can make an ערך
erech which are funds that go to בדק הבית? bedek ha-bayit? והתנינן
v'ha-teninan
היך מה דאת אמר תמן heich mah d'at amar taman so how
do you explain that according to רייש לקיש? Reish Lakish? You say
לשמים הוא מתכוון li-shemayim hu mitkavein ומאליהם הם באים או לבדק הבית
או לכלי שרת u-mei-aleihem heim ba'im o l'vedek ha-bayit o l'chlei shareit
that they're actually look, he doesn't know what he's giving. He just
says I'm going to give money. And we then decide how we're
going to use the funds. So he gave generic money. We wind
up using the funds for בדק הבית bedek ha-bayit or we wind
up using the funds rather than using it as operating funds we
actually buy something in the temple for it or we use it
to buy a כלי שרת. klei shareit. It wasn't a donation for
a כלי שרת. klei shareit. It was how we chose to use
the money and that wouldn't be a problem. כין את אמר אף
הכא kein at amar af hacha you say here also לשמים הוא
מתכוון li-shemayim hu mitkavein he's trying to bring an עולה with this
נסכים. nesachim. ומאליהם באים לבדק הבית או לכלי שרת. u-mei-aleihem ba'im l'vedek
ha-bayit o l'chlei shareit. You see obviously very problematic text here. The
basic point being that even according to רבי יוחנן רייש לקיש Rabbi
Yochanan Reish Lakish it's only he can't say I want this to
be used for this concrete object. For רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, that
it can't be a דבר מסויים davar mesuyam or even for רייש
לקיש Reish Lakish I want you to use this to help to
build some part of the temple, right, to בדק הבית. bedek ha-bayit.
But if I'm just giving money as a קרבן as an offering,
you know, you know, and you know especially the non-Jew. As you
see, right, you know, like, you know, we make all the money
itself is a type of an offering, right? They don't know what
you're going to use the money for; that's your decision. You want
to use it for operating funds, you want to use it for
קרבנות, you want to use it for בדק הבית, bedek habayis, for
דבר מסוים, davar mesuyam, that's not a problem because that's not what
they're—that's not allowing them to claim mistake. The concern is when they
can, according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, they can claim mistake that
my money went to build the building, and רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
when they can claim mistake and that object there that was my
donation. But when they—when they can't claim mistake, they're just generally giving
money and you decide what to do with it, that's okay. So
yes, Michael, if they actually didn't give their מנורה, menorah, but they
gave a thousand dollars and said, I want you to buy a
מנורה menorah for this and that's going to be my מנורה, menorah,
that definitely would be a problem.
Or even if they said, here's a thousand dollars, I want you
to buy something... put my name on the plaque, that would also
presumably...
but if they just said, here's a thousand dollars, use it as
you best see fit, you could go ahead and buy the מנורה.
menorah. All right, now, מה עבד ליה ריש לקיש? ma avad lei
Reish Lakish? Now, where does—what does ריש לקיש Reish Lakish do
with...
oh, so the question is, oh, so the question is I really
already anticipated the end. It says, okay, but I don't get it,
even if they're not giving it to a specific object, it's money,
in the case of ערכין, Arachin, it's still money that's going to
the Temple. So isn't that the same as אינו מסוים? eino mesuyam?
I mean, how does—how do you get out of the אינו מסוים
eino mesuyam for ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish? So פשט ליה, pashat lo,
he explains, no, לא לכם ולנו לבנות בית לאלוהינו. lo lachem velanu
livnos bayis l'eloheinu.
The problem is when it's going—this is what I was already saying—when
it's going to actually contribute to the house, to the structure itself.
So if he's just giving money and he thinks operating funds, nobody
ever wants to give to operating funds. You don't get your name
on operating funds. I'm going to pay—I'm going to pay for the
electricity bill. Okay, so—so he can give to the electricity bill. If
we choose to use generic operating funds for the—and then we're going
to direct it to the בדק הבית, bedek habayis, that's okay. But
for ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, even though he's a—he's a problem when
it's not a דבר מסוים, davar mesuyam, it's still only a problem
when it relates to actually the house itself. When it's very generic
funds and could be used for anything, then that—that money he will
accept. So fascinating issue here, and then the question of course becomes
how much does that translate outside of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
For ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish standard certainly seems to be a very
hard one to maintain. Even for רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan you can't
accept donations when people want a plaque by them—I mean, by the
way, think about the fact though that, you know, they had this...
well, no, forget it... I mean, in יומא Yoma you definitely find,
you know, the thing about like the מנורה menorah that was donated
by הלני המלכה Helni Hamalka and this thing that was donated by
this person. But they were all Jews, you know, but this idea
of like donating things and having your names on it, you know,
even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would not allow that. Okay, so that
we have as the debate.
We certainly do not follow that today.
Right. So just to remember, the משנה says Samaritans don't—even Samaritans don't
give to the שקל, shekel which is an interesting possibility that they
might be Jews, but we don't want them to give because this
is—they're a different community. But the גמרא basically assumes the משנה's assuming
that they're non-Jews. Then it says we don't accept from Samaritans and
non-Jews obligatory קרבנות. We accept from them free-will קרבנות, אדם כי יקריב
מכם עולה, adam ki yakriv mikem olah, but how about donations that
actually go to the building of the Temple itself, which is like
this פסוק in עזרא, Ezra, לא לכם ולנו לבנות בית? lo lachem
velanu livnos bayis? So there רבי יוחנן says the only thing we
won't accept is very specific דבר מסוים. davar mesuyam. Or well, we
won't accept at the beginning, that's the פסוק in עזרא. Ezra. Once
it's built, then we'll accept general things that go to the—to go
to the building of the house, but not דבר מסוים. davar mesuyam.
And ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says we won't even accept דבר שאינו
מסוים davar she'eino mesuyam if it is going to the building of
the house. Okay, yes, very quickly.
Yeah, Herod the Great built the last temple that we had. Yeah.
And his Judaism was...
all right, I don't know. Moving on. Okay. רב
חזקיה אמר רבי סימון. Rav Chizkiya amar Rabbi Simmon. So... שאל. sha'al.
So...
רב חזקיה אמר רבי סימון, Rav Chizkiya amar Rabbi Simmon, anyway, שאל.
sha'al. So רב חזקיה Rav Chizkiya in the name of רבי סימון
Rabbi Simmon asked the following question. He asks, do we not accept
from them for אמת המים amas hamayim or for חומת העיר chomas
hair ומגדלותיה? umigdoloteha? If you say לבנות בית, livnos bayis, maybe we
don't do anything that's permanent, maybe it's not limited to the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Maybe we won't accept contributions for the city wall
and for the towers. השם ולכם אין חלק. Hashem velachem ein chelek.
So to you know, so that you don't have a portion in
the building of the house. It's a funny question because it's בית
לאלוהינו, beis leloheinu, it's the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash anyway and doesn't
really get answered. Again, as you're seeing, very—does not have the smooth
flow of the בבלי. Bavli. You don't exactly know, you know, exactly
what the question was, did you finish, what was the answer? But
anyway, but it's not all a problem of the problematic text. Something
is just an issue that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi was edited, or finished,
a hundred years before the בבלי. Bavli. So a lot of the
smoothing out and the spelling out of things, you know, happened at
the last layer of the בבלי, Bavli, what we call the סתם
stam of the בבלי Bavli is generally assumed to be the very
latest layer and that helps the sort of the narr narrative flow
of connecting all of the statements. What you often get in the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi is you almost get like little tidbits and you don't
get, so what was the answer, what exactly was the question, what
was the answer, you know, you just sort of get very abrupt
things and partly it's because it didn't have a hundred more years
of development like the בבלי Bavli did. Okay, so anyway, yes.
It's almost like a shorthand.
Yeah, like you know the rest of the discussion, right, you know,
anyway, exactly. But that's it. I mean, these things obviously discussions occurred
in a context and the amazing thing about the בבלי Bavli of
the סתם is that it provides us more of the context. Not
100%, but a large part of the context. Okay, now we move
on to the קלבון. kalbon. תנן התם בתניא, Tanan hatam betanya, we
learned in a בריתא: braitah: אלו חייבין בקלבון, elu chayavin bekalbon, אלו
חייבין בקלבון אחד. elu chayavin bekalbon echad. The following are obligated in
one קלבון, kalbon, meaning normal people pay one קלבון kalbon in the
case of when you give a שקל shekel, for two people. Is
one קלבון. kalbon. רבי מאיר אומר שני קולבונות. Rabbi Meir omer shenei
kolbonot. Rabbi Meir says two. So the גמרא says,
דמתניתין דרבי מאיר. dematnitin deRabbi Meir. Our... the בריתא... braitah... one minute...
which בריתא? braitah? Hold on one second. Just
sorry one second.
Oh, so it could be the statement, it could be it's referring
to our משנה where it says, if you give a סלע sela
and get back a שקל, shekel, you pay two קולבונות, kolbonot, right?
And we ask why do you pay two קולבונות? kolbonot? You give
a שקל shekel you get back a סלע, sela, you give one
שקל shekel you get back a half-שקל, shekel that should just be
your one transaction fee. So why does it say that you pay
two קולבונות? kolbonot? So the גמרא says, דאמר רבי מאיר, deamar Rabbi
Meir, that's going according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. דאמר רבי מאיר
deamar Rabbi Meir because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, אף על פי
שאין שקלו תורה, af al pi she'ein shiklo Torah, even though...
קולבונות תורה. kolbonot Torah. So actually there's a very funny גרסא, girsa,
most standard גרסא girsa is that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, כשם
ששקלו תורה כך קולבונתו תורה, keshem sheshiklo Torah kach kolbonoto Torah, which
basically means that the קלבון kalbon is just as much part of
the
biblical שקל shekel as the half-שקל shekel itself.
Let's see what the גמרא says. Okay.
We'll see that's like the next line. Okay. סבר רבי מאיר במי
ששקלו שלם שהוא פטור מן הקלבון. Savar Rabbi Meir bemi sheshiklo shalem
shehu patur min hakalbon. Wait a minute, hold on, I gotta get
this text straight one minute.
Okay,
so they totally switched the גרסא. girsa. The way they switched the
גרסא girsa is בנותן שקל שלם שהוא חייב בקלבון. benoten shekel shalem
shehu chayav bekalbon. I mean it's completely changing אין to יש and
פטור patur to חייב, chayav, but the basic way that the מפרשים
here switch the גרסא girsa is סבר רבי מאיר במי ששקלו שלם
שהוא חייב בקלבון savar Rabbi Meir bemi sheshiklo shalem shehu chayav bekalbon
and not פטור. patur. דאמר, deamar, and now it gets
clearer, מתניתין דרבי מאיר. matnitin deRabbi Meir. You see how the text
sort of doubled itself over? Actually, I read the text in parentheses.
If we just skip the entire text in parentheses, it gets a
little bit better. So let's just jump to the end of the
parentheses. מתניתין דרבי מאיר. matnitin deRabbi Meir. Our משנה is רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. דאמר רבי מאיר, deamar Rabbi Meir, כשם ששקלו תורה כך
קולבונתו תורה. keshem sheshiklo Torah kach kolbonoto Torah. The same way the
שקל shekel is תורה, meaning like I said, I think one way
of explaining it is the משנה that says that when you give
a שקל shekel. and get back a half-שקל, you pay two קולבונות,
kolbonot, that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
even a half-שקל by itself you pay a קלבון. kalbon. כשם ששקלו
תורה כך קולבונתו תורה. keshem sheshiklo Torah kach kolbonoto Torah. קסבר רבי
מאיר בנותן שקלו שלם kasavar Rabbi Meir benoten shiklo shalem even when
you pay a normal שקל, like your regular half-שקל, שהוא חייב בקלבון.
shehu chayav bekalbon. Why? דאמר רבי מאיר, deamar Rabbi Meir, now we
finally get to the explanation: כמין מטבע של אש הוציא הקדוש ברוך
הוא מתחת כסא כבודו והראהו למשה. kemin matbe'a shel esh hotzi hakadosh
baruch hu mitachat kisei kevodo veher'ahu leMoshe. ואמר לו זה יתנו. ve'amar
lo zeh yitnu. This, just like this pure fire half-שקל you should
give. זה יתנו. zeh yitnu. Now what does that have to do
with a קלבון? kalbon? So the מפרשים, one explanation is, is it
means that that was completely, you know, nothing in this world is
perfect. Only the divine half-שקל was perfect. Anything in this world has
impurities. So therefore how do we give a type completely pure one?
You have to give an extra קלבון kalbon in order to make
sure that you have the full amount. So the idea here is
again the text is pretty corrupt or at least one version of
it, but the basic point is where the משנה says when you
gave a whole שקל and you got a half-שקל back, you pay
two קולבונות, kolbonot, why you paying two? It's only one transaction fee,
right? So it says no, that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says even a normal half-שקל you pay this amount to
round off a rounding
error. So when you pay it and you get it back, you
pay two. You pay a transaction fee that's one קלבון kalbon and
you pay the normal קלבון kalbon that you always pay with your
half-שקל in order that you make sure that it's a full half-שקל.
Okay. We will end here.